let's now move to some techniques for memory
allocation and let's start with contiguous
allocation so we know that
the main memory contains
the operating system itself and then the processes
of the users so now we are going to try to
answer this question how do we allocate memory
efficiently? and we start
with contiguous allocation
and then also go into segmentation and paging
we will see that there are trade-offs of
course as always and actually what I want
you to put attention to is that you will see
that the more we get to let's say complicated
memory management techniques basically
paging and virtual memory in the next lecture
the more we separate logical from physical
representations of memory and this has a lot
of benefits there is less fragmentation we
use memory better it's easier to protect the
processes and it also results in faster loading
and swapping of processes we would see now
these things one at a time so let's start
with contiguous application this is the most
basic thing you can do so you put the operating
system at the bottom of your memory and then
one process after each other giving
each process a contiguous set of addresses
this is just an example with three processes
and the operating system this
would be the the physical memory so now each
process has its own logical addresses they
start at zero and they go up to a certain
number and when we are running let's
say process A and A wants to access a certain
logical address which in this case will be
an offset we check whether this is less than
the limit for the process if no then we can
wake up the operating system so that it takes
care of this process that is trying to access
memory that does not belong to it if yes then
we sum the relocation register or the base
basically register that contains the first
address of process A the first physical address
of process A and then that the CPU can access
the memory and read/write in the physical
others of the memory because it is safe it's
accessing its own memory pretty easy but of
course as we discussed before using stuff
has always a cost and let's
see what the limitations
are when we terminate the process or we swap
out a process we leave a hole for that process
you need to keep track of which holes are
available at all times the operating system
needs to do that for other processes and this
results in potentially external fragmentation
what does it mean that it might be that if
we look at all the space we have available
so the sum of the sizes of all the holes we
have enough free space to put a process in
memory the problem is that if we look at the
individual sizes of the holes there is no
single hole that is big enough to contain
the process so the major limitation here
is that if you want to run a process but there
is no hole that can contain such a process
then basically you are done it might be that
you have a lot of free space so indeed you
could run the process if you just look at
how much space it needs but in practice you
cannot uh also you need to think about how
you take decisions uh when it comes to assigning
processes to whole or you can take the first
that is available pretty easy the first step
is big enough of course you can try to find
the best fit so basically the smallest hole
that is big enough to contain the process
the good thing if you do this is that
this algorith produces the smallest leftover
hole okay uh but of course you need to search
now so searching for something will take more
than just taking the first element
so going back to the pros here is basically
you don't waste a big hole to put a process
that is actually small
if you go to the worst fit the opposite
then you try to look for the largest hole
and this will produce the largest leftover
but again the price you pay here is
that you need to search the entire list
again as we will discuss more in the future
also for file system one of the complications
here is that you don't really know which strategy
is the right one or the best one until you
actually start running the system and discover
how many processes you want to run and how
big they are and how many holes you have so
there are different techniques you can use
the problem is that you don't really know
which one is the right one because to get
to know that you need to first actually run
the system and to run the system you have
to take first a decision about which strategy
you're going to use so you see that there
is like a conceptual loop here loophole that
makes stuff complicated when it comes to taking
decisions for the operating system and how
it manages
memory